<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Orders made and established by the Lords spirituall and temporall, and the rest of the general assembly of the Kingdome of Ireland met at the citty of Kilkenny, the foure &amp; tvventith day of October Anno Domini 1642 and in the 18 yeare of the raigne of our Soueraigne Lord King Charles, by the grace of God King of Great Brittaine, France, and Ireland &amp;c.</title>
            <author>Ireland. Parliament.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 26 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A46045</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing I426A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16395</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11854806</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11854806</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49952</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A46045)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49952)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 498:35)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Orders made and established by the Lords spirituall and temporall, and the rest of the general assembly of the Kingdome of Ireland met at the citty of Kilkenny, the foure &amp; tvventith day of October Anno Domini 1642 and in the 18 yeare of the raigne of our Soueraigne Lord King Charles, by the grace of God King of Great Brittaine, France, and Ireland &amp;c.</title>
                  <author>Ireland. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ireland --  Politics and government --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  History --  1625-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49952:1"/>
            <head>Orders made and eſtablished by the Lords Spirituall and Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, and the reſt of the general Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of the Kingdome of <hi>Ireland,</hi> met at the Citty of <hi>Kilkenny,</hi> the foure &amp; tvventith day of October <hi>Anno Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini</hi> 1642. and in the 18. yeare of the raigne of our Soueraigne Lord King <hi>Charles,</hi> by the Grace of God King of <hi>Great Brittaine, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>NPRIMIS, that the Roman Catholike Church in <hi>Ireland,</hi> shall haue &amp; enioy its priuile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dges &amp; immunities according to the <hi>Great Charter,</hi> enacted, or declared within the Realme of <hi>England,</hi> in the ninth yeare of the raigne of King <hi>Henry</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:49952:2"/>the third, ſometymes King of <hi>England,</hi> and Lord of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and afterwards enacted, and confirmed in this Realme of <hi>Ireland;</hi> and that the common Law of <hi>England,</hi> and all the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes of force in this Kingdome, which are not againſt the Catholike Roman Religion, or the liberty of the Natiues, and other ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects of this Kingdome, shalbe obſerued throughout the whole Kingdome: and that all proceedings in Ciuill, or Criminall cauſes shalbe according to the ſaid Lawes.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Item,</hi> that all, and euery perſon and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons within this Realme shall beare faith and true Alleagiance vnto our ſaid Soueraigne Lord King <hi>Charles,</hi> by the grace of God King of <hi>Great Brittaine, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> his Hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res and lawfull Succeſſours; &amp; shall vphould and maintaine his and their rights, and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full prerogatiues, with the vttermoſt skill, &amp; power of euery ſuch perſon and perſons, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all manner of perſons whatſoeuer.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Item,</hi> that the Common Lawes of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the ſaid Statute called the <hi>Great Charter,</hi> and euery clauſe, braunch, and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:49952:2"/>article thereof, and all other Statutes confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, expounding, or declaring the ſame, shalbe punctually obſerued within this Real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me (ſo farforth as the condition of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent tymes during this warre can by poſsibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty giue way thereunto,) and after the warre is ended, the ſame to be obſerued without any limitation, or reſtriction whatſoeuer.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Item,</hi> For as much as the Citty of <hi>Dublin,</hi> the vſuall and principall ſeate of ſuſtice of this Kingdome, where the Parliaments, and ordinary Courts were held, and ſome other places where the Prouinciall Councels were ſometimes kept, are as yet poſſeſſed, &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded by the malignant Party, who are enemyes to God, their King, and all his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties well affected ſubiects; this Aſſembly is neceſſitated, during this warre, in ſome for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malities and circumſtances, to deuiate from the proceedings preſcribed by the ſaid Lawes and Statutes, yet neuertheleſſe retayning the ſubſtance, and eſſence thereof, ſo farforth as the endleſſe malice and cruelty of their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, the ſaid malignant Party, doth permit,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49952:3"/>who shut vp the ſaid places, and all other paſſages and wayes to his Maieſties iuſtice &amp; mercy, from his Maieſties well affected ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects of this Kingdome: For the exaltation therfore of the Holy Roman Catholicke Church, for the aduancement of his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties ſeruice, &amp; the preſeruation of the liues, eſtates, &amp; liberties of his Maieſties true ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects of this Kingdome, againſt the iniuſtice murders, maſſacres, rapes, depredations, rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beries, burnings, frequent breaches of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blicke fayth and quarter, and deſtruction, daily acted and perpetrated vpon his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties ſaid ſubiects, and aduiſed, contriued, &amp; continually executed by the ſaid malignant Party, ſome of them managing the Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and affaires of Eſtate in <hi>Dublin,</hi> and in ſome other partes of this Kingdome, to his Highnes greateſt diſseruice, &amp; complying with their confederats the malignant Party in <hi>England,</hi> and elswhere, who as it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt to all the world, doe complot and practiſe to dishonour, and deſtroy his Maieſty, his Royall Conſort the Queene, their Children,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49952:3"/>and Monarchicke Gouerment, which is of moſt dangerous conſequence to all the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narckes, and Princes of Chriſtendome: The ſaid Aſſembly doth order, and eſtablish a Councell, by the name of <hi>Supreme Councell,</hi> of the confederate Catholiks of <hi>Ireland,</hi> who are to conſiſt of the number of foure and twenty, to be forthwith named by this Aſsembly, wherof twelue at the leaſt, to be forthwith named, shal reſide in this Citty, or where elſe within this Kingdom they shall thinke ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient; and the members of the ſaid Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell are to haue equall votes, and two partes of three, or more concurring preſent votes, to conclude; and no fewer to ſit in Councell then nyne, wherof ſeauen at the leaſt are to concurre. And of the foure and twenty a <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident</hi> shalbe named by this Aſsembly, who is to be one of the ſaid twelue reſident, and in caſe of his death, abſence, or ſicknes the reſt of thoſe who shalbe reſident may name a Vice-preſident of the foure and twenty; and this Aſſembly is forthwith to name a Secretary, and Clarke of the ſaid Councell, the Secreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49952:4"/>to be of the ſaid foure and twenty; and the ſaid Councell shall haue the powers and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminences following (vz.) That Lords-Generalls, and all other Commaunders of Armies, and Ciuill Magiſtrates and Officers, in the ſeuerall Prouinces, shall obſerue their Orders and Decrees, and shall do nothing contrary to their directions, and shall giue them ſpeedy aduertiſment, and account of their proceedings and actions, with as much expedition as may be. That the ſaid Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell shall haue power to order, and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine all ſuch matters, as by this Aſſembly shalbe left vndetermined, and shalbe recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended vnto them; and their orders therin to be of force vntill the next Aſsembly, and after, vntill the ſame be reuoked. That the ſaid Councell shall haue power and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to queſtion, and inflict condigne punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vpon all Commaunders of Armies ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted from the powers of Generalls, and vpon the Generalls themſelues, and vpon all Gouernours, Magiſtrats, and other perſons, of what degree or quality ſoeuer, and vpon
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49952:4"/>any of themſelues, in caſe of delinquency. That the ſaid Councell shall haue Power &amp; Authority to doe, and execute all manner of acts, and things conducing to the aduance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Catholicke Cauſe, and Good of this Kingdome, and concerning this warre as if done by this Aſſembly; and shall haue power to heare, and determine all matters Capitall, Criminall, or Ciuill, excepting the right or Title of Land. That the Generalls and other Commaunders of Armies, and all Gouernours and Ciuill Magiſtrats, and all other perſon within this Realme, shall obey the orders and decrees of the ſaid Councell, touching the preſent ſeruice. That the ſaid Councell shall haue for their guarde the number of fiue hundred foote, and two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred horſe, to be equally extracted out of the Armies of the foure Prouinces.</p>
            <p n="5">5. It is further ordered, and eſtablished, that in euery Prouince of this Kingdome, there shalbe a Prouinciall Councell, and in euery County a County-Councell, the Prouinciall Councell to be compoſed of the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49952:5"/>number of two of ech County, and the ſaid Prouinciall Councell shall chooſe a Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of themſelues.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That the Prouinciall Councell shall ſit foure tymes a yeare, and oftener if there be cauſe for it: That they shall haue power and authority to reuiew, or reuerſe the Iudgments or Decrees of the County-Councells, the party complayning entring ſecurity <hi>de adiudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caris ſoluendis:</hi> And shall during the troubles, haue power to heare, and determine all mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the Crowne, as Iudges of <hi>Oyer,</hi> and <hi>Terminer,</hi> and <hi>Goale-deliuery</hi> were wont to doe, ſo that no Spirituall perſon be preſent at the determining of matters of bloud. And shall haue power to heare and determine all Ciuil Cauſes, and to eſtablish recent poſseſsions, ſo they meddle not with title of Land, other then in caſe of <hi>Dower,</hi> or <hi>Ioyntures.</hi> And the Sheriffes, Prouinciall Generalls, &amp; all Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunders of Armies in caſe of diſobedience, are reſpectiuely required to execute their decrees and orders; and in caſe of debts and accounts great conſideration is to be had of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49952:5"/>the disability of Creditours occaſioned by the warre.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>Item,</hi> in euery County, there shalbe a County-Councell conſiſting of the number of one, or two of ech Barony, at the election of the County; and where there are no Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, the Councell of ſuch County to be of the number of twelue; and the ſaid County-Councell, shall haue power &amp; authority, in all points as Iuſtices of Peace, to heare &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine all matters concerning the office of Iuſtice of Peace, &amp; all matters of the Crowne happening within euery ſuch County, &amp; the delinquent being a Freehoulder, may if he pleaſe haue his triall in the Prouince; and to heare and determine debts, treſpaſſes, &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall demaunds, and to doe all things as Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices of Peace were accuſtomed to doe; and to reſtore and eſtablish poſſeſſions, taken by force or fraude ſince theſe troubles; &amp; like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to take eſpeciall care, that Tenants and Farmers be kept to their Farmes where they were vſed, and be preſerued from extortion and oppreſſion; and that Trade, Tradesmen,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49952:6"/>Manufactories, Agriculture, and Husbandry be maintained, and Markets duely kept.</p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>Item,</hi> that in euery County there shalbe Coroners, high Sheriffes, high Conſtables, petty Conſtables, &amp; Goalers, who are to doe their reſpectiue offices as accuſtomed; the high Sheriffe to be confirmed, or nominated by the ſupreme Councell, out of three to be preſented by the County-Councell; and the High Sheriffe is required to execute the Commaunds, Orders, &amp; Decrees of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinciall, and County-Councell.</p>
            <p n="9">9. <hi>Item,</hi> in Cittyes, and Townes corporate; Iuſtice is to be done, and the Law executed as accuſtomed.</p>
            <p n="10">10. <hi>Item,</hi> in euery County the high Sheriffe shalbe Prouoſt-Marshall, and shall haue power to execute a Layman not worth fiue pounds, and none other, for murther, man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaughter, burglary, theft, robbery, or other capitall offence: Prouided the perſon to be executed, may haue foure and twenty houres tyme to prepare his ſoule; and that the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Councell, or Prouinciall Councell,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49952:6"/>shall, &amp; may name more Prouoſt-Marshalls, as they shall thinke expedient, qualified with the like authority.</p>
            <p n="11">11. <hi>Item,</hi> it is further ordered and agreed, that no temporal Gouerment, or iuriſdiction shalbe aſſumed, kept, or exerciſed within this Kingdome, or within any Prouince or Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty therof, during theſe troubles, other then as before is expreſſed, excepting ſuch Iuriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and Gouerment, as is, or shalbe appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued or inſtituted by this generall Aſſembly, or the ſupreme Councell.</p>
            <p n="12">12. <hi>Item,</hi> it is further ordered, that whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer hath entred ſince the firſt day of October 1641. or shall herafter during the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuance of the warre in this Kingdome, enter into the Lands, Tenements or Hereditaments of any perſon, or perſons who haue beene in poſseſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſuch Lands, Tenements or Heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, at, or immediatly before the ſaid firſt of October, either by himſelf or his vnder te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, or by receauing of the rents, iſſues, or profits therof, shall immediatly vpon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund reſtore the ſaid poſſeſſion to the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49952:7"/>or parties ſo put out, with ſuch reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble domages as the County, Prouinciall, or ſupreme Councell shall thinke fit: and if the party refuſe to reſtore the ſaid poſſeſsion, ſo gained as aforeſaid, vpon demaund of the party ſo put out, his Heires, or Aſſignes made to the ſaid poſseſsor, his ſeruants, or adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents in the premiſses, or publication of this order within the Parish, where ſuch Land lyeth, that vpon his, or their deniall therof, or default therin, he, his heires, and Aſſignes shall for euer after be debarred and ſecluded from all and euery right, title, intereſt, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund which he, or they may make, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to all, or any the ſaid Lands, Tenements or Hereditaments: and if after ſuch deniall or default made, the ſaid party, his Heires or Aſſignes, shall not immediatly reſtore the poſſeſsion of the ſaid Lands, Tenements, or Hereditaments ſo gained, to the party grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, his Heires or Aſsignes; that then he, and they, and his, and their adherents in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes, shalbe declared, and proceeded with as enemies. Prouided, and ſo it is meant, that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:49952:7"/>if any of the ſaid parties ſo put out, be decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a Newter, or Enemy by the ſupreme, or Prouinciall Councell, to the generall Cauſe; that then the party who gained the poſseſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion as aforeſaid, shall giue vp the poſseſsion to ſuch perſon, or perſons as shalbe named either by the ſaid County, Prouinciall, or ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Councell, to be diſpoſed of towards the maintenance of the generall Cauſe, vpon the paine and penalty aforeſaid. And as for the Rents, &amp; maine Profits of the ſaid Lands, Tenements, and Hereditaments, &amp; all kind of Rents, Goods, or Chattles taken or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained from any Catholike as aforeſaid, due ſatisfaction is to be made for the ſame, to the parties from whome the ſame Rents, Goods, or Chattles were, or shalbe taken or detai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, ſince theſe troubles began, as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinciall Councell, or County-Councell shall reſpectiuely order.</p>
            <p n="13">13. <hi>Item,</hi> it is further ordered and eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed, for the remouall of all Ciuill diſorder and enimity, and to the end all men may bend their thoughts and actions to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49952:8"/>Cauſe, that all poſſeſſions of Lands and Hereditaments shall continue, and remaine vnto ſuch as haue allready ioyned in this vnion, as they haue beene for three yeares paſt; next before the beginning of theſe trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles; and that no title of Land shalbe drawne into any debate or queſtion vntill the next Aſſembly, other then in caſe of Morgages, Leaſes, and particular eſtates <hi>de facto</hi> determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, or determinable by effluxion, or other determination therof.</p>
            <p n="14">14. <hi>Item,</hi> for the auoyding of Nationall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction betweene the ſubiects of his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Dominions, which this Aſſembly doth vtterly deteſt and abhorre, and which ought not to be indured in a well gouerned Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth: It is ordered, and eſtablished, that on paine of the higheſt Punishment which may be inflicted by authority of this Aſſembly, that euery Roman Catholike as well English, as Welsh, and Scottish, who was of that profeſsion before theſe troubles, and who will come, and pleaſe to reſide in this Kingdome, and ioyne in the preſent vnion,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49952:8"/>shalbe preſerued, and cherished in his life, goods and eſtate, by the power and authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and force if need require it, of all the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes of <hi>Ireland,</hi> as fully and freely, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Natiue borne therin, and shalbe acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and eaſed of one third part in three parts to be deuided, of publicke charges and leuyes raiſed, or to be raiſed for the maintenance of this Holy warre.</p>
            <p n="15">15. And it is further ordered, and eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed, that there shalbe no diſtinction, nor compariſon betwixt old <hi>Irish,</hi> and old or new <hi>English,</hi> or betwixt ſepts and families, or bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wixt Cittizens or Towneſmen, and Contry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ioyning in this vnion, on paine of the higheſt punishment that can be inflicted by any of the Councells aforeſaid, according to the nature and quality of the offence, and diuiſion like to ſpringe, &amp; ariſe from thence.</p>
            <p n="16">16. <hi>Item,</hi> it is further ordered &amp; eſtablished, that all new Conuerts, borne in any of his Maieſties dominions, or elswhere (without manifeſt occaſion giuen) thoſe perſons con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted to the contrary, and ioyning in this
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49952:9"/>cauſe, shalbe accounted as Catholike Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, to all intents and purpoſes.</p>
            <p n="17">17. <hi>Item,</hi> it is further ordered and eſtablis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hed, that all Artificers, Artizans, Nauigators and Marriners not being denizens, who shall pleaſe to reſide in this Kingdome, shall during their reſidence in this kingdome, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſuch tyme as they, and their families shalbe here ſetled, haue and enioy the free li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties and priuiledges of Natiues in all reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects.</p>
            <p n="18">18. <hi>Item,</hi> it is further ordered and eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed, that whereas, in regard of the preſent eſtate, and condition of the Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> no Natiue of this Kingdome, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if he be a Catholike, or any other Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike, is there admitted of, or permitted to continue in the Innes of Court; and to the end the laudable lawes of <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> may not dye amidſt the diſaſters of the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes; that one Inne of Court shalbe erected in ſuch place of this Kingdome, as the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Councell shall thinke fit, for the tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vp of the Gentry of the Kingdome to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:49952:9"/>the knowledge of thoſe Lawes.</p>
            <p n="19">19. <hi>Item,</hi> it is further ordered and eſtablis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hed for the aduancement of learning, that in euery Prouince of this Kingdome, Free-Schooles shalbe erected and maintained, ſo many, and in ſuch places, and in ſuch manner and forme, as to the Metropolitan, and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary of the Dioceſſe, in the reſpectiue Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces, shalbe thought fit.</p>
            <p n="20">20 <hi>Item,</hi> it is further ordered and eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed, that no Lords, Gentlemen, or other perſons shall raiſe, or keepe any Companyes of ſouldiers, or troopes of horſe, but ſuch as shalbe authorized by the ſupreme Councell, Prouinciall Councell, or County-Councell, or Magiſtrate within their owne Corporate Towne: and that the Statuts againſt Ceſſe &amp; Conye or Liuery, be duely put, in execution: And that no company, or ſouldiers whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer shalbe payed, or relieued by the County excepting ſuch as are, or shalbe enrolled in the Marshalls liſt, and none shalbe billetted but by the Conſtables.</p>
            <p n="21">21. <hi>Item,</hi> it is further ordered and eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49952:10"/>that Church Lands and Tithes impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priate in the hands of Catholike owners be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore theſe troubles and ioyning in this cauſe, may be left to them according to their ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall eſtates, vntill the ſame be diſpoſed of by Parlame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t; they in the <hi>interim</hi> anſwering their rents as accuſtomed.</p>
            <p n="22">22. <hi>Item,</hi> it is further ordered and eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed, that the Kings Cuſtomes, Rents, Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes, Arreares, and Duties, and the rents, iſſues, and profits of Lands, and Heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and Goods and Chart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es of Enemies and Newters, which are, or shall be declared by the Prouinciall or ſupreme Councell, or by the generall Aſſembly, be receaued and collected, and be diſpoſed for his Maieſties vſe and ſeruice.</p>
            <p n="23">23. <hi>Item,</hi> it is further ordered &amp; eſtablished, that in euery County, there be Collectours, and Receauers to be appointed by the County-Councell, and that they be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table vnto the ſaid County-Councell for the ſame, which County-Councell shalbe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable to the Prouinciall Councell ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:49952:10"/>halfe yearely, and the Prouincial Councell to the ſupreme Councell yearely, to the end the ſame may not be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cealed, or miſapplied.</p>
            <p n="24">24. <hi>Item,</hi> it is ordered and agreed, that where any Arch-bishops, Bishops, or other Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie, or any perſon, or perſons whatſoeuer, hath, or enioyeth any Lands, Tenements, or Hereditaments, Tithes, or Church-liuings, in one County or Prouince, or hath, or shall keep his, or their Reſide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in another Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or Prouince, that in all ſuch caſes the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits accrewing out of ſuch Lands, Tenements, or Hereditaments, tithes, or Church-liuings to the generall vſe, shalbe imployed within the ſaid County or Prouince, where the ſaid Lands, Tenements, and Hereditaments ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes or Church-liuings doe lye, as by the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall County-Councells reſpectiuely shalbe thought fit, for the publicke cauſe.</p>
            <p n="25">25. <hi>Item,</hi> it is ordered and eſtablished by the ſaid generall Aſſembly, that any woman being a Roman Catholike, and wife to any Proteſtant, or Catholicke, that hath forſaken his houſe, eſtate, and wife, and adheres vnto
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49952:11"/>the Enemie, that euery ſuch wife may enter into her loynture, if any be conueyed vnto her, or may recouer the thirds of her ſaid husbands eſtate, as if her ſaid husband were actually dead; and that euery ſuch wife shalbe in ſuch condition and capacity to ſue, and to be impleaded, as if her ſaid husba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d had been exiled, or abiured the Realme by iudgment of Law, except the Prouinciall, or ſupreme Councell in particular caſes, order the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</p>
            <p n="26">26. <hi>Item,</hi> it is ordered and eſtablished, that the poſſeſſions of the Proteſtant Arch-bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops, or Bishops, Deanes, Dignitaries, and Paſtors in the right of their reſpectiue Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, or their Tenants, in the beginning of theſe troubles, shalbe deemed taken, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrued as the then poſſeſsions of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Arch-bishops, Deanes, Dignitaries, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, and their tenants reſpectiuely, to all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents and purpoſes, and that thoſe poſseſsions are intended within the precedent order for ſetlement of poſſeſsions.</p>
            <p n="27">27. <hi>Item,</hi> it is ordered and eſtablished, that
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:49952:11"/>no man being priſoner by authority of any of the Councells aforeſaid, shalbe enlarged without the order of the ſaid Councells reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectiuely, and that no protection be giuen to ſeruants, or other men of the Enemyes party, without the like order of the chiefe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunder of the Army, in the ſeuerall Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces, or Countyes.</p>
            <p n="28">28. <hi>Item,</hi> that whereas abuſes haue beene committed in ſome parts of this Kingdome in taking of Armes, Ammunition, or other Merchandizes, from Merchants arriued in Creekes, or Harbours, far from their inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Port, by reaſon of tempeſt, or the danger of the Enemye, to the greateſt diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the merchant: It is therfore ordered &amp; eſtablished, that where any ship, or ships, or other veſſell shall come, or arriue in any Harbour, Bay, or Creeke within this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, laden with Armes, Ammunition, or other merchandizes, that in ſuch eaſe, all thoſe that are, or shalbe in Commaund in the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iacent Countyes reſpectiuely, shall protect, and defend the ſaid merchants, their goods,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:49952:12"/>and ſeruants, and shall at the charges of the ſaid merchants, procure carriage for the ſaid goods, and ſafely conuey the ſame to the ſaid Merchants intended Port, and not to ſuffer any of the ſame, vnder colour of paying for the ſame, or otherwiſe to be diſpoſed of, or taken, before the ſame come vnto the inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Port, and be entred into the liſt of the Commiſſioners, by the expreſſe direction in writing of the ſaid Commiſſioners: and that any who shall robbe, ſteale, or violently take any of the ſaid goods, contrary to this order, shalbe deemed, and punished as Enemyes to the publicke good of this Kingdome, and ſuffer death therefore.</p>
            <p n="29">29. That certaine Commiſſioners shalbe appointed in euery Port-towne, of the Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, &amp; Reſidents therin, by the Prouinciall, or ſupreme Councell, for the viewing of all the armes, &amp; ammunition that shalbe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after imported into this Realme from beyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Seas, and to certifie the ſame to the ſupreme Councell with all ſpeed; and to preuent abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in the ſale, or iſſuing, or diſpoſing of them.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:49952:12"/>
            <p n="30">30. <hi>Item,</hi> it is ordered and eſtablished, that where Souldiers doe run from their Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, or Commaunders, vnto other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or Prouinces, that the Commaunder, or chiefe Gouernour of the ſaid County or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince, vpon complaint made therof, shall ſend backe the ſaid fugitiue Souldiers to their Commaunders, to be dealt with, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to luſtice.</p>
            <p n="31">31. <hi>Item,</hi> it is ordered and eſtablished, that the debts, and other duties owing to credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of this vnion, by Newters, and Enemies, shalbe payed out of the goods, Lands, Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and Hereditaments of the ſaid New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and Enemies reſpectiuely, before any other publicke charge be anſwered therout.</p>
            <p n="32">32. <hi>Item,</hi> it is ordered and eſtablished, that no Souldier, or other perſon, without Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund from the County-Councell, shall meddle with the Goods, or Lands of New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, or Enemyes.</p>
            <p n="33">33. <hi>Item,</hi> it is ordered and eſtablished, that to preuent the ſpringing vp of all Nationall diſtinctions, the Oath of Aſſociation, or
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49952:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>Vnion be taken ſolemnely, after Confeſſion and receauing of the Sacrament, in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish Churches throughout the Kingdome; and the names of all Perſons of ranke and quality in euery parish, who takes the ſame, be enrolled in Parchment, and be returned, ſigned and ſealed by the Parish Prieſt, to the Ordinary of euery Dioceſſe, who is to keep the ſame in his Treaſury, and to certifie a coppy therof vnder ſeale to the Metropoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, who is to keep that, and to certify a true coppy therof vnder his Metropolitan Seale to the Rolles of the Kingdome, where the ſame is to be enrolled.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Exam. per Richard Shee: ſupr. Conc. Cler.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
